Back to the slides,
but the same examples
that we just saw
in the other video.
And that is, first of all, here's
the example that I had noticed that for
this marking that we see here,
t2 and t3 are activated concurrently.
The intuition was that that was
because I could sort of grab these
two tokens and move them
through t2 and t3 simultaneously.
That was the intuition
for that kind of parallelism.
But strictly speaking, the term
is defined mathematically, by this definition:
So I actually have to do
the math that in each case this
relation holds, for the example
and for the other examples.
Let's
do that.
What would be the relevant
pre-weight functions in this case?
The preweight functions
of t2 and t3.
And I'll write each of
those down in tuple notation.
We fix ourselves on the
place order s1, s2, s3, s4.
Then, for example, the
pre-weight function of t2
is exactly the function which can
be written down as the 4-tuple (0,1,0,0).
Because exactly only of s2
here is an input arrow.
And analogously at t3
the preweight function is (0,0,1,0).
Because
of this
input arrow going from s3 to t3, and
because there are no other incoming arrows after t3.
That explains these
two statements here.
Now, to prove that
t2 and t3 are concurrent,
you have to sum
these two pre-weight functions.
And this is done with this
sum symbol, which performs element-wise additions.
That is, what is
on the left here would
be the vector addition of
these two 4-tuples, that is, (0,1,1,0).
And in that case, it turns out
that this is exactly equal (less-equal would do,
but it is even exactly equal in
that case) to the marking (0,1,1,0), which
also turns out if we take
the current marking of this Petri net.
Because on s1 there is
nothing, on s2 there is
something, on s3 there is something (and exactly
one token each), on s4 there is nothing.
That means, here this
criterion is exactly fulfilled.
Therefore we can also say:
t2 and t3 are activated concurrently.
In the previous video, I
had also discussed what would
happen, for example, if one were to
create another arrow from s3 to t2.
And then we
had seen first:
Then t2 and t3 would
no longer be activated concurrently,
because the requirements for t2 and those for t3
would get in each other's way, so to speak.
Because you can send this one token either to t2
or to t3, but not both at the same time.
What would this mean
for the mathematical version?
Nothing would
change for t3.
But by the additional arrow from
s3 to t2 something changes for t2.
Namely, this additional arrow turns
this 0 into a 1.
Because the arrow must be
represented/reflected in the pre-weight function.
And that would be this 1 here,
because t2 then requests a token from s3.
So there would be a 1
here, where my cursor is currently pointing.
The sum would result
in (0,1,2,0) instead of (0,1,1,0).
And (0,1,2,0) would not be
less than or equal to (0,1,1,0).
Even if there would be more tokens on
s4, so that the sum of the tokens
in this marking would be much
larger, there would still be simply
the problem concerning this only one
token lying on s3 by (0,1,2,0).
What I had also already
discussed in the video was:
However, if one then put
down a second token on s3,
then t2 and t3 would again be
activated concurrently, because then that was enough.
Then you would send a token
up here and send one to
t3, and that's
not mutually exclusive.
That would correspond to the situation
where we have (0,1,1,0), here (0,0,1,0), the
sum would be (0,1,2,0),
and that would be okay.
If there was at least a 2 here,
which would correspond to the second token on s3.
So there, what I
intuitively tried to observe simply
graphically on the Petri net itself,
regarding t2 and t3, coincides with what
the mathematical definition (which we had here
on the slide) gives for this example.
And that will coincide with each
of the other examples as well.
The next example
was this example here.
There we
had found
that t1, t2, t3 are all
three activated concurrently, for this marking.
Not only can there be two, but (this
also showed up on the slide) there can be
more than two transitions in this
set T', so they can be concurrently activated.
If that condition
is satisfied here.
Is
it here?
So this assertion from the
previous video that t1, t2,
t3 are concurrently activated, can that also
be verified by doing the math?
Well that's very
easy, very straightforward.
All three preweight functions for t1, t2,
t3 are each exactly the function that
says to take a token
from s1, and that s2, s3,
s4 are irrelevant to the
possibility of firing the three transitions.
Then we have
these three pre-weight functions.
Their sum
is exactly (3,0,0,0).
And it is again the
case that this exactly coincides.
There comes out in sum (3,0,0,0),
and that is exactly equal, and
therefore also smaller-equal, than
the marking to be seen.
This is because we have
as many tokens to consume.
Not too many,
not too few.
Many would
not be bad.
If there were 4 here,
the "less-equal" would be fulfilled.
But "too few" would
just prevent firing, or
prevent the concurrent
activation of all three.
It is also clear, of course,
that t1, t2 are also activated concurrently.
We could ignore t3 and
say: t1, t2 are activated concurrently.
Because if we just add the pre-weight
functions of t1 and t2, (2,0,0,0) comes out.
This is also
less-than-equal to (3,0,0,0).
This again agrees with this observation from
here that if a set of transitions
is concurrently activated, then it also
holds for any subset of them.
Then I had the example where
I actually removed one of the tokens.
So where we have only two tokens
left in s1 at the beginning, but
the rest of the
Petri net is unchanged.
There we
had already said:
Then it can no longer be the
case that all three are activated concurrently.
In fact, for this example we then get
that pairwise each two of the transitions are
activated concurrently, but not
all three at the same time.
So every two-element set, which we
can form over transitions, is a set,
where the transitions shown in it
for this constellation are activated concurrently.
However, this is not true for
the total set t1, t2, t3.
We
see:
We cannot use these two tokens to
satisfy t1, t2, t3 all at once.
What does
this mean mathematically?
Here again, t1, t2, t3
all have the same pre-weight function.
Namely, this one that we also
just had on the previous slide.
And it's also true that in
each case the pairwise sums of
two pre-weight functions give
a marking, namely (2,0,0,0), which
is nowhere undercut by
the marking shown here.
So this is true for any
combination of two of the transitions.
However, if we take all three transitions, we
would also have to make this triple sum.
That would be (3,0,0,0), and that is
not less than or equal to (2,0,0,0).
That's why that's not enough, or t1,
t2, t3 are not all three activated concurrently.
Then we
had this example.
I'm not going to do the math
there again, although of course you could.
In that example,
we had discussed that
one of each of the two transitions with
t3 is concurrent, but t1 and t2 are not.
Unless, of course,
one added another token.
So we
had stated:
The sets \ and also \ are
in each case activated concurrently, because the firing of
t3 is just as it were contact-free
to the firing of t1 and/or t2.
But not \ together and consequently
not \ all three together.
Because then again
would be valid:
If t1, t2, t3 were activated concurrently, also
t1, t2 would have to be activated concurrently.
But this is not the case, because we
cannot satisfy t1 and t2 at the same time
with these three tokens (because of
this only one token in the middle).
This is what
I had discussed.
With one more token
it would be possible.
Then t1, t2 and t3
would actually be activated concurrently.
We had
also discussed this.
What this example still shows is
that unlike causality (as discussed at the
end of last week), the
notion of concurrency is not transitive.
So it's like this here:
t1 and t3 are concurrent, t3
and t2 are concurrent, but
t1 and t2 are not concurrent.
It was
different with causality.
If t1 was necessary condition for t2
and t2 was necessary condition for t3,
then t1 was also
necessary condition for t3.
This is not necessarily analogous for
three transitions with respect to concurrency.
So much
for the examples.
Then I'd like to briefly
discuss some properties, some observations about
concurrency, before we get to the
notion of conflict in the next video.
One observation is (I had also gone through this
in the video on an example) that if we
have such sets and a
marking, so that the transitions of
this set are activated concurrently,
then any arrangement of the transitions
is a valid firing sequence starting from
m. This is the case with the set.
I had discussed this exactly on the
example for the case that we put
another token on here, so that t1, t2,
t3 were activated concurrently, all at the same time.
Then you could also fire in any
order: t1, t2, t3; t1, t3, t2; etc.
I had then written that
down, all possible firing sequences.
All six that would be
possible as permutations of t1,
t2, t3, and
that's a general observation.
So if I have a
set of concurrently activated transitions, then
we won't look at a firing sequence
as firing in parallel (because the firing
sequences are always listings of transitions),
but at least then any sequence
of the corresponding transitions
is a valid firing sequence.
So any sequence
in which each transition
from T' occurs exactly once
lets us fire from m.
Not that we
get stuck somewhere.
And out comes a marking
m', and that's always the same.
So for an m and any set
of concurrently activated transitions, it can't be that
if we change the order of the
transitions from the set when firing, we
somehow come out
at a different result.
This also speaks for
this at least conceptual consideration:
It's kind
of parallel.
We're writing
down firing sequences,
but the order between
these concurrently activated transitions doesn't matter.
In the end, the same thing comes
out unless we do something else in between.
It's really just
a matter of:
If we have this set T'
of activated transitions and we execute them
from a marking m in any order
(again, you could have seen this in the
example that was in the video; because no
matter what marking would be on here and
no matter what order I
then fire t1, t2, t3), the
result is that in the end there is
exactly one marking on each of the subsequent places.
That would be a case
where this becomes effective and visible.
This ensures that in the one example at the beginning
of the last video, which I think we had already
seen, in the reachability graph then
always a kind of arrangement of transitions
will result in such a
way for transitions activated concurrently.
There I had had
that before for two transitions.
I think they were t2 and t3
in the causality example from last week.
Namely, if we have
something like this, very
simple, two obviously concurrently activated
transitions, and we set
up the reachability graph just for
this example, then it looks like this:
There is
this square here.
I have also said
"diamond" to it before.
It depends on
how you draw it.
Higher dimensionally, it will look even more
obvious, so to speak, like a crystal structure.
The point
is here:
Since t1, t2 are activated concurrently,
the order doesn't matter.
That means, from any marking (in
this case the start marking of
this very simple Petri net) we can
fire first t1, t2 or t2, t1.
And it results in this
typical structure, which we find here,
if we have
concurrently activated transitions.
That's because the
order doesn't matter.
And as
I said:
If we have more than two
transitions, then that just becomes something
like a higher
dimensional such mathematical construct.
So for instance if we have
that, but just also in other Petri
nets where we have three concurrent transitions
(and that doesn't have to be as obvious
or as boring as it is here,
but is true for any constellation where
we have three concurrently activated
transitions), then such structures arise.
Again because any order of
transitions will be possible, and
that then leads to such
structures in the reachability graph.
Maybe, or usually, of course
embedded in larger reachability graphs.
But you can
then recognize that.
And then that speaks to
the fact that there is concurrency.
That's not proof of it, but it's a
certain identifying feature that you can look for.
Then you can ask yourself if that's
sort of guaranteed that there's concurrency if
you see a structure like that, or
if you know that all the transitions from
a certain set are fireable from
the same marking in any order.
So if we have a marking m
and a set T' such that any arrangement
of these transitions is a valid
firing sequence, is it also the
case that with certainty the transitions
from T' are activated concurrently for m?
This is the converse of
the observations we just discussed.
And the
answer is:
No, that's
not necessarily true.
And here's
a simple counterexample.
You can use the
example to think about:
If we take here \
as the set T', then of course
any order of
firing is possible.
We can fire t1, can fire t2, we
can fire t1, t1, can fire t2, t2.
The t1 and t2 are always activated,
but t1 and t2 are not activated concurrently.
This can be
checked very easily.
Because for that we would have to be
able to fire t1, t2 at the same time.
So we would have to be able to fulfill
the preconditions of t1 and t2 at the same time.
But we can't do
that with this one token.
And even if we recalculate this
with the preweight functions, we would
have the preweight function
1 in each case.
There is
only one place.
So a tuple
with a 1 each,
the sum would be 2, but the
current marking just has only one token.
So here t1, t2 are not activated
concurrently and yet it is the case that
they can be
fired in any order.
That's ultimately due to
this loop structure here.
Of course, this is
a somewhat mean Petri net
here because it has this
loop or two such loops.
By loop (or loops) we mean when there
is a transition and a place, so that
this transition would like to take
something out of this place (so
it has a positive pre-weight)
as well as put something in
if it can fire (so
it also has a positive post-weight).
This leads exactly to such
structures in the Petri net.
Of course, the Petri net does
not have to look exactly like this.
This can occur somewhere
embedded in the Petri net.
So other arrows
are possible, to
other places or in
connection with other transitions.
But if we have a Petri net
in which such a thing does not occur
(in which there are no loops),
that is, we have a loop-free
Petri net, then the question from the
previous slide can actually be answered positively.
So if we then have a
marking and a set of transitions
such that any arrangement of these
transitions leads to a valid firing
sequence, then this set
will also be concurrently activated.
So then we can actually conclude from
the presence of, say, a "cube" that
there is a three-element
set of concurrently activated transitions.
We will not
have to do that.
Whenever we have such questions
("Is there something concurrently activated?"), we
can calculate
it concretely.
Of course, our criterion in each case
will be to determine that with this.
Or if you have done that often
enough, you will of course recognize the things
from the Petri net itself,
and you don't necessarily have to
calculate that manually, as I
just did on the slides.
That's enough for the end of the
consideration of concurrency from the formal side.